software engineering radio episode 37
extreme programming part 1
[Music]
hi everybody
great to have you all listening in once
again today it's Alex and Arno talking
about extreme programming Alex this was
actually your idea so I suggest you just
dig right into things yes the idea of
doing an extreme programming episode and
the development process episodes first
is because expiry has well there's a lot
of pass around XP actually and it's in
my opinion kind of the very minimal
development process we have so it's a
good starting point to see what we have
and have a process where you actually
can't take anything out of the process
without getting into trouble so it's a
good starting point in my opinion I
think this is quite an interesting claim
I think we will need to take a closer
look at that later yeah cause it's a
strong claim that we cannot take
anything out but yeah I agree and we'll
get into that when we were looking at
the practices in the details yeah we
should nevertheless extreme programming
is well you just may be the wrong word
but there's a lot of things we should
talk about so I guess we will have two
episodes covering XP the first first one
doing the principles and all the basic
stuffs and actually the the practices
which are the heart of extreme
programming I guess we will do the the
big-picture stuff and how all the
practices relate together and how our
process stuff and all this in the second
episode so let's start as already said X
piece had some started some hype I would
say the the HR movement so it's very um
it's a hot topic there are really fans
of XP and and guys who don't like it at
all so it there's a lot of emotion in XP
we try to stay on the the fact side I
hope at least yeah have you ever
actually worked with Kent Beck have you
have life experience with him no no's
unfortunate I once have the privilege of
doing perhaps
ramming with him and he is a guy who can
really polarize people I mean at one
point he actually yanked away the
keyboard from me slapped me all the
hands I said test-first emotional
aspects of extreme programming go back
to Kent Beck and I mean the word extreme
programming sort of support supports the
hype aspect which i think is great
because it helped the agile movement in
getting coverage but then again it was
starting to be a problem at one point in
time because yeah it's sort of um well
had the taste of it's not really to be
taken serious it's not for serious
programming which i think is bad because
agile development and extreme
programming do really do work and
commercial and good projects yeah
exactly
but as you said I still think it's it
was one of the greatest ideas to call it
extreme programming I don't think we
would have the the HR movement where we
have it right now without such a well
emotional and name so it's it's not just
another per development process it's
something special from the name from the
beginning so um it helped a lot I guess
yeah so what is XP well first of all
it's an incremental and iterative
development process we talk a lot of
about these words and what they mean in
the first development process of a few
episode so go back there and and listen
to what it means me if you don't or if
you are not comfortable with the both
words was invented in the late 90s by
Kent Beck and it can ID refer to the CCC
project now the Chrysler comprehensive
compensation is that what you're
referring to exactly at least that's
what I heard was the first real extreme
programming project nevertheless the
three say they they used a lot of the
practices of XP and earlier projects to
and and actually a lot of the stuff you
find in the smart or community so
the name extreme programming and the
whole concept as one development process
goes back there but but the chorus Solar
yeah this is the story that I heard is
that of course many of the practices go
far back far beyond that project and at
the beginning of the project XP did not
exist and sort of the process gels
became a an explicit process the course
of this project yeah yeah and
nevertheless still experience what I
wouldn't say rapidly changing but it's
changing and we will get into trouble in
our two episodes too with this topic
because there are two editions of the
whether the basic extreme programming
book from camp back and actually the sec
it's called extreme programming
explained like embrace change we will do
a link to our side assistance notes yeah
yeah and the second edition actually is
very very different to the first edition
it's nearly a complete rewrite so we
have some trouble and to decide which
well which version of XP we really
discussed and I guess we will yeah go
into details on some of the topics we
write which is sort of funny because in
the right especially beginning in the
first years extreme programming people
were really very strict about you need
to be exactly this otherwise you cannot
call extreme programming yeah but things
sort of mellowed out and it's think it's
it's very important that it actually
evolved and the discussion got beyond
this yeah you need to be everything
exactly by the book staged that's right
but nevertheless I would also recommend
to start with an X sect XP copy whether
worsen one or two doesn't matter so much
but we will get into this some other
practices of XP arm well they can do
harm if you don't do another practice
which actually give some synergetics
between the two practices so it's a good
idea to start with a whole set whether
version one version two doesn't matter
so much to me actually yeah
what I suggest to just sort of dig in I
think the heart of XP are the values
behind extreme programming as at least
that's what Kent Beck says in the book
and I think that works quite well yeah
are those prayer those values
well maybe we should explain what well
use our fork and back and he defined it
they are universal they are
complementary they're consistent and
purposeful so what does that mean well I
think what Murray's trying to get at is
that they are sort of having an
objective side to them and they're not a
matter of taste
yeah but idea is that they go go beyond
personal taste that you the team needs
to have these values consistently in
order to achieve a purpose and that they
sort of universal like every team that
should have them at least every good
working team and they are the basis that
everything else build or builds on
exactly and they are well I would call
it a system of well yesterday there yeah
the idea is that they complement each
other so if you change out one of the
the well use actually you have to order
you can get into trouble so and always
take these values as a complete system
of values well actually I think it goes
beyond that because values are not
something that you sort of pick up for a
project and then dump for the next chunk
I think this is at a personal level I
think the idea is that the core team
needs to actually have these values as
part of their personalities and then the
idea is that others also change deep
inside as other personality level to
actually take these things as as values
of their own not just for the
professional side during the project
absolutely and so it's a first likeness
test if you can deal with extreme
programming I would say because not
every company I know will get warm with
all the values of XP actually so I would
recommend to check out the values and as
you said it's a personal saying if you
don't
you comfortable with all these values
maybe XP isn't the best thing for you to
start with okay let's dig in what are
those values yes
maybe I listed them first up and then we
can discuss a bit of them so to get this
system feeling a bit
they are communication simplicity
feedback courage and respect so if if
you take these values actually and look
at the h-hi manifest you you see the the
well they they fit very well together so
you see the familiarity these ideas the
communication thing the simplicity thing
the only the simplest thing that could
possibly work which is a strong sense
and a sentence and highly discussed
sentence because we do this simplest
thing that could possibly work doesn't
mean to the simplest thing actually and
a lot of people get this sentence wrong
and say oh yeah the simplest thing
doesn't work for me you shouldn't do it
yeah right exactly like like
documentation um agile is not don't do
any documentation just discard the
documentation you don't need yeah
absolutely important thing here of to me
personally to me is the courage thing I
guess at least well I'm my first expect
it's a long time ago and actually XP was
very well not so famous at this time and
it actually takes courage to do it right
that because a lot of the practices are
contrary to - to the beliefs and the
stuff you learn at your universities how
to do things so I guess courage is a
huge point for doing speed not so much
today maybe but in some companies still
I would say right exactly
courage sort of takes you by surprise
when you first hear it you say courage
is an important part of developing
software yeah
but I agree it's a very important thing
and um the the credits go to extreme
programming for making that explicit
yeah maybe we should give
examples I mean actually it takes
courage to do such little documentation
to don't think contract-based with your
customer two together a team feeling
with your customer and and share the
risk with them which is contrary to to a
lot of business belief actually where
you try to fix everything in a contract
and afterwards if something goes wrong
you know at least who who's the one who
did the wrong thing so everything a bit
different to a lot of cultural stuff in
the business world hmm and also at the
technical level it does take courage to
say I think we went into an entirely
wrong direction for the last two or
three weeks we need to throw away what
we didn't start over this is the sort of
thing yeah one of the values is feedback
and as we be taught very very much in
the first development process episode I
wouldn't go into detail here but the
feedback stuff is well very very
important to iterative and incremental
development and feedback is necessary
for gaining knowledge for change
changing requirements it's it's simply
the core for the empiric process stuff
just to get them back right I think if
it's actually the role of the project
manager in XP to provide feedback to do
measurements to provide feedback to
guide the team by providing feedback and
not by making the decision herself but
by confronting the team with the
consequences of alternatives which sort
of goes back to the courage thing
because you know leading in that way it
does take courage yeah I was worried er
sound when I first well when I did my
first experience people checked how much
you do with well measurement actually I
mean most of the projects I did before
were well you do your software you do it
as good as you can and when it's done
it's done but you do you you collect a
lot of numbers while doing XP and you
calculate your your speed you develop
speed and calculate how much of your
feature set you will be able to do until
a special time point so it's very very
different on this point yeah exactly I
think we should sort of try getting to
what XP what XP actually looks like I
think we've got the mindset that is
behind that is the basis for things you
need to value communication you value
simplicity and you need to value well
your feedback actually confront yourself
with whether in a decision was
successful or not they have courage to
change the direction and you need to
respect one another so where do we go
once we have these values well the
values are the very very basics of XP
and they have still one comma I don't
know how to call it abstract thing above
the values but these are more concrete
than the where is already they are
called principles and principles are
actually the definition says they are
widely applicable they are
domain-specific whatever that means I
mean we get a bit into this when we see
some of them they can be contradictory
in contrast through the values which
shouldn't and they should be concrete
enough to to guide your behavior and one
thing and we already touched it before
is strangely now they changed from the
first book to this second book nearly
completely so I'm maybe we should look
into the ones from the first book first
and then touch the ones from the second
edition just to add a full picture but
you will see all of them first or second
book will fit to the same well yes so
that it's it really fits the definition
so the idea is sort of to break down the
values into more hands-on more detail of
things to guide behavior
I said yes yeah actually so in the first
book there there actually were five
basic principles first one is rapid
feedback which well
easily maps to the the value of course
then assume simplicity in chronemics to
a value yeah exactly
incremental change which is interesting
embracing change also very very
interesting and the book itself it's
called embrace change so very strong for
XP and quality work so what touches me
actually is the quality work thing
because it's I think a lot of developers
do want to do quality work and XPS where
much on their side it's very they were
not eccentric on this point because this
it says you have to do quality work to
to get to keep your speed to to make it
work to do non-trivial software and
quality actually is not an option in XP
very very interesting thing I never read
this in another development process that
yab strongly yeah I mean also XP is sort
of one of the strictest processes you
know it requires developers to sort of
submit themselves to a common go to
achieve this quality and be and yeah
this is I think quality is really at the
heart of extreme programming yeah well
we will see this in the practices too as
I mean it started the unit testing
movement which are already is sweat over
the whole development world not only the
XP guys do unit testing anymore so it
make this movement famous or or great
embrace change very important thing in
my opinion the XP was built to to fit in
environments where you have mmm changing
requirements maybe even fast changing
requirements so you you have to deal
with the fact that requirements change
that's actually a huge difference to
some of the other development process
where you try to fix the requirements as
good as you can and XP says regardless
how much work you put into this we will
try to fix the right
months they will change that's a matter
of fact and yet because I think we'll go
to that in more detail the second
episode oh you have you the connection
between programming the business and
overall picture good idea and of course
incremental change to deal with changing
requirements you have to be able to to
do incremental change to your software
actually so these were the basic
principles from the first book should we
discuss the the smaller ones also go
into them when we looking at the
practices because they are reflected in
the practices good idea yes in the
second book there actually is a complete
or a huge set of principles there and I
don't think we should really dig into
deep exactly I mean we look at those
principles in rabaa we looking at the
practices they'll pop up one again and
again exactly nevertheless maybe I
should give short overrun over them to
to give an idea how they look like
I mean they are still based on the same
value system so the principles in the
second edition of XP de them new one is
our humanity economics mutual benefit
self similarity improve improvement
diversity reflection flow opportunity
redundancy of failure quality baby steps
we will touch all of these ideas
actually when we discussed the practices
so yes as you said we shouldn't go deep
in there right now right but before we
go to the practices there's one little
story I'd like a child um Kant said once
that you asked people after an extreme
programming project what was most
important to them what for them was the
best part of doing extreme programming
and he expected people to give technical
things like we did quality work or that
sort of thing or we met our budget
constraints but what people said was
when Harry had when Harry's wife got
sick he could just leave out for a
couple of days and stay with her and
that sort of things outside the the
actual work is really part of the XP
you know extreme program is not just
about getting a job done but it's about
values about things that touch the life
outside the idea is that program has
developers every member of the team is
not just replaceable is not just a
number but is valuable and these things
are really really important and I think
it's very important to keep that in mind
before we dig into the practices because
the practices are about mace mostly
about getting the job done but the other
things are the basis for these
principles for these practices that
actually build on the values you know
absolutely humans are not resources that
can be easily exchanged as some other
processes you know yeah yeah ok so what
are the practices now it's becoming
juicy because this is actually a thing
that is most prominently known about
extreme programming ok for the practice
the same problem a bit different
additions of XP this time will stay with
a second edition we have a complete list
here so I mean we should go into the
chase with them because they are more
newer ones ok I suggest we first go
through them one by one and then we look
at how they interact
ok yes fine first one sit together well
all of the maybe we should say first
every practice has a name so sit
together is the name of the first
practice actually so sit together well
the idea is easy sit you or make it easy
to to communicate between the people and
you remember the values so put all the
people if possible into one room
communication is essential for for
development and the cost of
communication should be low and
therefore the easiest thing is to put
them in a one room of course which is
quite a controversial practice
especially on developers I mean put 10
developers into a team into a single
room and usually the know
level will go up so far and the joking
will be so loud that nobody can actually
get much work done because everyone
keeps everyone else from working so this
requires discipline on the part of the
developers you know to sort of
unrespected others take back themselves
to enable the others this is sort of a
prerequisite which goes back to the
values that is a prerequisite for ever
actually having the whole team in one
room exactly and it's just or I will put
it another way this is one of the
practices that doesn't make much sense
if you don't do some of the other
practices as well I mean if you take
your team put it in one room and still
you have a team that isn't a team
actually team ten people who work for
each other with no communication you
just raise the noise level you have no
of the private of benefits so sitting
together of course just makes sense when
the people really work together so you
have to do pair programming and all this
stuff and to make it purposeful and
sense for you
maybe you should mention that having
people in one room means really one room
no cubicle walls or something yeah one
big open space with people sitting at
desks all over the place with easy
access from one to the other so this is
really about not having any private part
for any single developer yeah um so this
is really being together in it this is
an expression of we're together
and there's no such thing as I win you
lose as we win together or we lose
together yeah yeah
and actually because it is I mean you
can could imagine that it's hard if you
have no privacy anymore that's why they
they recommend you to - yeah make some
point some rooms free in your building
where you can do your email stuff alone
or what I contrived yeah so it's not
again for this exactly it's not about
removing all privacy it's just that you
know in the work space privacy is not
the primary concern but yeah the
togetherness is the primary concern when
you do team work do it best I mean this
yeah
one of the that's why it's called
extreme programming because they took
all the best practices so-called best
practices and maximized them out they
put on all the knobs on ten like can peg
light that's caused it that's what he
likes to say in the marketing talks yeah
okay but that brings us to the same
practice I think I'm having the whole
team together yeah which doesn't mean of
you your team shouldn't be separated by
the functions of your team's put all
your people together to the requirement
engineers or whatever you have put them
all to in one room let them work
cross-functional together so everyone
actually actually there are no
requirements engineers right yeah but
there are on-site customers maybe
testers whoever works in your team so
require the classic requirement
engineers aren't there but you have well
you have the chopped to do so you do
your user stories and stuff like that
and separating people out to do user
stories and only user stories and put
them in an extra room and put your
on-site customer and an extra room bad
idea not the idea of XP of course so the
project manager and everybody sits
together in this single big room with no
cubical partitions sort of taking the
open-door policy to the extreme yeah and
of course you could imagine that doesn't
work too good for a 200 person team so
hundred person ever is a team yeah but
nevertheless I guess we have to say it
at some point the at least in the first
book there was a limit set for to up to
10 or 12 people and where XP works best
right actually in the second book is a
bit softer with us limit as we already
have yeah huge teams doing XP they do it
of course not in the the uncustomed way
they build cluster sub teams whatever so
second edition says ok you
can also do large projects huge projects
with XP but first edition and and all
the the primary practice are well the
idea is to work in a small team right I
mean it is definitely possible to do
agile development with really huge
projects and I see a trend from the
first book to the second book the first
book was very clear XP means having
these practices with an actual team size
of 10 or 12 people max and the second
book sort of wanted to expand the scope
and sort of softened the definition of
extreme programming to include other
kinds in a bigger variety of agile
development agile development is
definitely possible for any size of
project and extreme programming I think
we can we are safe to say extreme
programming is best fit for actually one
team that you can sit together in one
room yeah and actually I that's what I
like a lot about the first edition of
the book it was very clear about when to
use it when not to use okay so um let's
look at the third practice which is
about how to organize the workspace
mm-hmm well simple idea use your
workspace I mean you have wars in there
you have desks in there just use it use
use post-its to put or white papers put
them on your wall stick them on the wall
so use the space you have best for your
work
very easy ideal nevertheless you know
some of the companies have very strict
regulation on how to use your office
space Yeah right
kind of stupid actually someone once
told me that he when he came into a
company I'm not going to name the
company now they wanted to do extreme
programming but they had big office with
cubicle walls so they sort of one one
morning before everyone else arrived
they brought power tools from home and
took down the cubicle walls of maximize
the use of their workspace what happened
to the team they got away with it they
got away with it so yeah this sort of
this spirit that um this
rebel spirit we have together be wanting
we're well gelled and we are together
and BR the rest of the company is not
this sort of thing tends to happen with
extreme programming I think courage
again carriage again and again the idea
is we want to work as good as we can so
we're going to do whatever it hit it
takes to work well and make use of
anything we can if words if we don't if
the words are in the way of our team
communication we'll take them out and if
you need whiteboards we'll put them up
and that sort of thing yeah yeah
actually when you said this I remember
one of the ideas of XPS you have to play
to win too if you want to do XP not play
to play or play not to lose you have to
play to win actually it's it's a
different idea how to do your project so
which is again which is again an
interesting thing that we'll look at in
the second episode I think because
winning can mean different things to
different people
yeah but I think we are we'd better
leave that for the big picture in the
second episode okay next thing energized
work I guess it was called 40 hours a
week only I'm not sure but that what
what's the idea the basic idea is in
between NIT a lot of teams work very
long hours and actually you have to to
do well you can have to know your limits
and it doesn't matter if it's actually
40 hours or 44 hours or 38 hours that's
not the point here and at the point is
work as much or as little and to stay
focused to to have energy energy enough
to work on the next day with the same
energy level and you don't work for
sprint intervals but for for long
distance runs we go at a sustainable
pace yeah exactly
which also means I mean there's another
side to this coin which which says which
means um yeah don't to pressurize people
to spend many hours at the office but
also make good use of the hours that
actually are at work yeah which because
I mean many of the practices like pair
programming especially or being in even
being in one office room tends to put
yeah tends to help focus on actually
working yeah and and yes alright the
first weeks I remember when I did per
prepare programming where I couldn't do
any After Hours it's very it's hard to
do actually it's exhausting you actually
be disciplined about taking time off
between programming in order to
re-energize you cannot do that eight
hours on end brings us to the next
practice pair programming actually oh
that's what is pair programming yeah
the idea is to developers one keyboard
again best practice for this is code
review and it's done to the extreme but
its head has more benefits than than
just code reviews the idea actually is
that to developers code each non-trivial
part of code together and you always
have a peer who looks what you do if you
do it right and actually the the error
level kills is so much lower than you
ever could believe it will do the design
will get better and even naming stuff
and a lot of sloppiness scales away with
this but it's it is exhausting it's not
for everyone actually and it's a hot
topic a lot of people don't like it
about actually I have to say most of the
people who don't like it didn't really
try it out for a longer period of time
so which only Alan is ittle unfair
because if people try it out for two or
three days and they hate it and go each
other's throats yeah of course sort of
sort of unfair to say you didn't like
you should try it for another week
well the point nevertheless is it sounds
awful actually
I mean the first time I heard it and and
someone did want to do it with me for
for real project work not not hobby
programming
I was very whoa I didn't feel very
comfortable the idea having someone sit
besides me and looking at every thing I
do the whole day so it it sounds very
very bad and actually it isn't that bad
at least not as bad as it sounds there
are pop maybe we should shoot this cap
discuss the practical stuff before a bit
before we discuss the wine well people
stuff on this one yeah actually pair
programming doesn't mean you you get
your friend and let them sit besides you
for the whole day and he doesn't do
anything besides staring at your screen
you have to change the peers and you
have to change it often actually the
time period is from five minutes to a
few hours and after a few hours you
should really change the peering so you
mean I think that two things that change
over time one is you're not working
together with the same person all the
time but you switch the teammate with
who you sit before the keyboard which
means um one day you sit with both Alex
next next in the afternoons it with Mary
and on the third day you sit with Ben so
it's really you change the people there
are no fixed pairs but the other thing
that changes is the roads roads change I
mean if you're sitting obviously it's
not that doesn't work very well to
people type on the same keyboard at the
same time so one the mouse and one the
keyboard it doesn't really work well one
has the master of the keyboard
um so often these are true roles one
person actually does the typing the
other sort of looking and reviewing and
commenting yeah the person who is type
and often tin ports in a low voice not
not to astrub others but still both sort
of discussed things they're doing it all
the time but the important thing is to
change the keyboard actually every
couple of minutes yeah there are
situations when it makes sense to for
one person to keep the keyboard longer
than that but actually yeah if so if I'm
typing and alex has a good idea to do
things differently I shove the keyboard
so he implements his idea and
this changing is one of the hardest
things of pair programming and actually
of extreme programming I think the idea
is to have egoless programming and there
is no such thing as code ownership yeah
if I code something it does not belong
to me but the idea is quite the contrary
if I have a great design idea um the
best thing that can happen from an XP
point of view is that someone else
implements it and all the team is able
to change it later because everyone
understood it this is a pair programming
together and the idea is to get the job
done you get good software done not to
play to play not to have fun I mean it
is fun but the idea is not fun for its
own sake but to program as effectively
as possible and for that it's good idea
to share the design to share the code in
the who team who get to testing like
your own tests first
which is good prerequisite was it but um
one more thing necessary I would say
definitely necessary as these practices
go together but still um the idea here
is no one owns code so there are code
conventions that everyone shares so
everyone feels at home with all the code
and if I have a job I want to get done
let's say Alex designed the reporting
subsystem and I want to fix a bug that
effects the reporting subsystem then the
obvious thing to do is for me to
approach Alex and Alex I'd like to quote
together with you when do you have time
I like I need to get a job done on the
reporting subsystem and your you know
that better than me
so we sit together and work on that so
it's a very natural way of transferring
knowledge um in in many projects um I
would suggest approach and say there's a
bug please fix this in the reporting
subsystem it's habit when you're
finished or or even worse you call your
pro project manager - - yeah get anyone
to fix it I mean right exactly it's not
really I mean we're used to it already
but it's not so common in business world
that
one developer gets another one and and
they didn't fix it together actually
exactly depends on the team culture and
the size and things but here's the idea
is actually for em that the best the the
goal that everyone's driving it is that
all the people are familiar with all the
code so that anyone can change and fix
anything and since that is off not not
entirely the case it it's an established
best practice if you want to work on
code that you are not absolutely
familiar with that you don't feel
comfortable changing you could just get
someone who knows that code better and
then you will learn about the code and
feel more comfortable working on it the
next time and this really requires a
value system of communication of getting
the job done of respect for one another
yeah and in my experience this is the
single biggest hindrance the biggest
single obstacle in implementing extreme
programming um that um there's a culture
of cowboy programming it is cool to be
the tough guy - this is my code hands
off who changed my design and did such a
great job and you messed it all up that
sort of thing and there's just no room
for that in extreme programming I'm
actually gland and yeah so this is eco
this programming the idea is the team
gets the job done
and um this is not about hedging of
staking your claims inside the project
there's no room for that in extreme
programming people I either give up this
sort of staking their claims or they
won't fit into an NXP team so he sound
very emotional actually um there was a
project I worked I was actually
protected and I try to implement it to
programming started very carefully so I
paired up a good friend of mine with
someone else actually we we use cast it
and everything so okay we'll give it a
try and they sort of went at each
other's throats because they were both
the head vote very strong egos okay and
so yeah I am speaking for experience
here it does have an impact on your on
the values on the private values of
every single person working on the
project yeah really I have
agree completely it'd be our programming
is really it's really a hard thing to do
don't underestimate it theory I get I
guess it's then one of the major points
were expedient reduction of an extreme
programming into a team phase very often
or a team doesn't well is not the right
team for extremely running to end on a
positive note if you actually do
implement pair programming and it does
work yeah it is such a great experience
it brings you together with the team it
creates so much trust such a feeling of
we're together we can do anything
actual feeling of or such such respect
for one another like everyone knows the
strengths and weaknesses of other people
so there's nothing to hide from one
another you learn from each other you
learn from one another and you also I
mean it
there isn't much less pressure on single
members of the team especially in tough
phases of the project I mean we all know
the sort of thing in a big deadline is
approaching and I designed the the
database access layer and implemented it
so there's a problem with the database
access layer um I'll be the one working
through the nights because so what else
can
let's sort of thing or also finger
pointing and blaming you made that
mistake just happens a lot less so it's
a really really rewarding experience to
work in pairs it just means that you
have to adapt sort of deep down within
for it to work I agree completely and
pepper cramming is one other it's great
it's and there are the social benefits
you already mentioned there are the the
harsh facts of course the you you have
less a lot less bugs in your code you
have an as management or customer you
don't have the problem that only one guy
can do fix your back or whatever so the
drug factor yeah oh yeah the track
factor might explain track vector okay
that means how many people need to get
run over by a track for the program for
the project to fail sort of how many
people share share important knowledge
or how centralized is important
knowledge in the heads of one person
alone the track factor of one means I'm
the only one who can't do something sort
of Ameren over by a truck the project
will stop and fail yeah exactly but
playing the so so I also would say pair
programming is great it's simply great
absolutely but playing devil's advocate
here you have the problem you have to
explain management that to guys doing
the chop for one how would you react to
this I mean I mean a to developers one
keyboard or you could get the idea you
only have half the productivity yeah but
yeah I think this is important thing in
introducing this and I think we should
look at that both at the management
level and the team level let's start
with the management of what you just
addressed um I think the key thing here
is quality of the software and actually
that is what extreme programming is
about hmm having software that has a
continuously high level of quality so
that the pay's i mean if if there is
then inside quality room is reduced the
code goes bad if the software design
tends towards chaos the productivity
goes down at least the final days before
a deadline for delivery because it's
very very there are bugs and they're
very difficult to fix and if you fix one
bug problems pop up in seemingly
unrelated places that sort of thing so
the many of the practices of extreme
programming especially impaired
programming and test-driven development
are focused on spending effort in the
beginning in order to maintain a high
level of quality and reduce risk so
those are I think terms that management
is able to understand you know I mean if
they actually do value um quality
there's an amazing number of men
who either don't value quality or who
have heard so many promises about coffee
that they actually don't believe you but
the important point here is actually
that the quality is not for its own sake
as you said and the idea even in XP the
idea is have quality to keep speed up
that is that's the point you have to do
incremental change and you can only do
incremental change and architecture and
all the stuff on the way or by Lu by by
doing the project by trying to change
your requirements if your quality is up
you don't have any chance to do it
otherwise so quality is not nice to have
factor to have happy customers how some
could yeah take a look at quality it's
essential it doesn't work without
actually yeah very very important point
yeah yet yeah or one or do you have
other points for for the management or
whatever few on pepper cramming because
I want to give one last or for my sad
last comment on how to introduce pair
programming because one of the major
major points done wrong when introducing
pair programming is not leaving space
and and time and places for for people
to relax and calm down I mean at the
team level now let's sort so say the
management gave their okay you may do
pair programming how do you actually win
a team and introduce pair programming
into the team so the team actually digs
in and does it it likes it
exactly so yeah how do you do that well
my first of all it's always great to
have someone in your team who already
did it nothing can compare to that so
try to get what someone who does know
how to do it
but if you don't like that sort of try
to do it yourself ask people to join you
at your table at your desk and sort of
share the keyboard with them so as to
gain the experience yourself exactly
second point is start slow
don't start with eight days eight hours
a day pair programming do it one hour a
day in the first two three days to land
two hours and so get up to to the
maximum level that actually fits your
your power and team whatever and then
third point leaf leaf spare time and
places you have to it's it's constant
stress level actually when you do pair
programming because if you program for
your own you have times where you just
can relax for a few seconds and then
concentrate again to to code that
doesn't work when you do pair
programming actually because your peer
actually asks you or points you to to
some puck you you're introduced or
whatever so it's constant stress level
and yeah you have to introduce their
time in between and and exactly I'm to
relax and communicate explicitly that it
is okay and it's wanted by management
you know and it's absolutely okay to say
now let's take a break yeah mmm-hmm
actually there's one one additional
obstacle which in my experience is one
of the biggest obstacles to pair
programming in practice and that is sort
of um silly but it's really a big
problem because many desks are all
shaped at least at least in the in the
in Germany and where I have been working
and it's the screen and keyboard tend to
sit in the corner of the L so that you
have all the big part of the desk for
your papers and this is a pet program
just does not work on a desk like that
with the screen in place in the corner
so if you want to introduce a program
the first thing would be to move the
screen in the keyboard and the mouse to
a part of your desk where two people can
comfortably sit beside each other um we
sort us the same um spatial relation
through the screen and have the kyboot
can can actually pass the keyboard from
one to the other and have room enough
for that which is a step you actually
need to actively take in most office
environments that I know yeah
another thing I would recommend in if
you don't do pair programming because
usually you do pay a deeper at least a
normal protein good point yeah if you
ask too many many desks maybe many
screens I sort of had to stand behind
the person who asked me to help sort of
was hard to even read what was on the
screen
yeah very very good point yeah do this
yeah
teams to that workers team together
office environment and and and and desk
layout and placement of screen and
keyboard are just different for
programmers then for administrative
people so yeah has a courage to change
your desk layout so let's jump to the
next primary practice primary practice
that's called test first programming
yeah great this is one of my personal
favorites akia my personal favorite I
have yeah and actually it's it's it's it
became so important Kent Beck wrote
another book on it and said this is one
of the course or the the programming
core of XP and be done even without XP
so you can leave out all the process
stuff and the user story stuff and
whatever and still test shows
programming does help a lot mm-hmm
so what is test first programming well
very simple it's write a test then write
the code that satisfied the test and
then refactor but I guess we have to go
a bit deeper that okay first of all test
in this context means having a unit test
yeah sort of using one of the frameworks
J unit or CPP unit or n unit I think
it's been ported to many languages as
port for pints and for Ruby um just the
idea is to actually have write code that
called the code as you you put you write
a class or a method or something and the
test is other code that calls the code
you want to test and then checks the
result if they come if they are what you
want them to be so you do not just run
write a class change something and then
start the entire application and then
sort of go through the user interface
and
look if the behavior is what you expect
it to be I mean that it's okay to do
that but testing in this context means
having code that tests your code in a
repeatable automated way you have code
as you start the code says thumbs up
your code is good thumbs down there's a
bug in your code it's important that
it's automatic and the other thing is
actually that the unit is tested I see
this a lot in projects I work done wrong
where whole subsystems are tested and
the class
connects to the database would you have
to set up your server ID exactly and the
point is really test just for one simple
single method you see act right right
more right but I think we're going to do
an entire episode on unit testing yeah I
will go into the there's huge it's huge
area very important stuff very relevant
there's plenty of things to say but we
leave that for the other episode yeah
time now
yeah but important samarium port just
test the single thing you will write in
the few seconds afterwards a lot more
right exactly so lets you code your your
test and then afterwards you code your
code yeah but actually this is the sort
of the the pure doctrine of Kent to say
you first write the test and then only
when the test is finished you start
coding your actual code yes this is a
good practice but I in my personal
experience I think it doesn't make much
of a difference if you sort of I often
do it in a close change I start with a
very simple implementation which I don't
really put much effort into then I write
some tests for the basic cases and then
I do them and usually I though my code
isn't a perfect medical code and then I
start to think about special cases and
then to the tests look if the code does
it that sort of thing so it's more like
jumping from one to the other
yeah I don't think it's very important
to first finish the test and only when
the test is finished you start actually
coding but the important thing is to
actually do it more or less at the same
time because if you leave it for too
late you'll never do it yeah
I guess that's where the idea for this
streak test first thing is coming from
because a lot of people well they will
not write any tests when they once once
they've written their business logic so
right and that's it's more and well
philosophical or psychological provide I
don't know it's it's sort of a way to
get started to help your own discipline
and also many people if they first write
their code they're used to sort of
manually testing it mmm and I mean this
is effort that you just don't have to do
if you actually write the test yeah yeah
yeah the other networking thing there is
once you you write it in this way very
close to together your your tests and
your codes you you chain get different
interfaces but I guess we will just cast
this in a test first episode really
vital but it changed your code it's
really a quality thing quality aspect
here more than just automated tests yeah
exactly that was just what I was going
to say so okay if we actually had the
same idea exactly I think this is really
really important because if you want to
test your code at a fine-grained level
at the unit level this influences your
design it helps to actually modularize
your design because when you want to
test a single class there's sort of
notice that there are hidden
dependencies two big other parts of the
system which in my experience usually
happens if you do not do unit tests so
someone's once said you test first
um development is um way of is a way of
designing a system and I think there's a
lot of truth in it because good
testability tends to be good decoupled
design so what yeah I think we'll leave
the the details of the of how to do this
for the test-driven episode but there's
one more thing about test-driven design
I think which is which is relevant here
and that is um you actually achieve
eight
sweet which is a collection of classes
sort of code that can test more or less
whole system and this is a very valuable
thing because it gives you flexibility
it helps you to make changes in a
confident way and which is the Auto
basis for non-trivial refactorings yeah
it's it's this technique makes some of
their other practices possible otherwise
it wouldn't work to do yeah global code
ownership and all this stuff
mm-hmm yeah exactly exactly yeah sure so
yeah the idea is if I change someone
else's code if I reflect the code
someone else wrote and the tests
afterwards still say thumbs up
everything is fine then I can be
confident that I didn't break anything
this is sort of the UM the level of
confidence you have should have with
this with the tests um and this is also
an indication of the coverage you need
to achieve but just to illustrate how
valuable this sort of thing can be I
once worked on a system which was which
did asynchronous communication and had a
database at the back end and was highly
scalable all these sort of things and
the business requirements sort of
changed quite frequently every couple of
days things fundamentally changed so we
had but we had time to do really really
good coverage with the tests and we were
so confident that we if the if a change
request came in that it required a
change to the database we made the
change to the database and then retested
the system and from the moment we
started our work once we had the change
requirement and the time when we were
finished and said this system is again
ready for release was about half an
hour's time and we were really confident
that everything worked just fine which
was a really great way of working it was
fun um there was no pressure there was
no fear because we sort of we felt
whatever happens we're on top of things
this is the sort of fun that test-driven
development gives you know I've never
seen a team doing it
real test yeah you even unit testing and
in a real good way and getting back
afterwards
yeah right but take care if someone
tells you unit testing doesn't work if
it is really you're interesting because
I've seen it done wrong often much too
often and exactly I mean and the things
you can't do wrong and how to avoid them
will be in the other episode yeah yeah
me maybe we should just take a few
seconds to discuss the third part of
this first program refactoring I guess
we will do an other episode on this
stuff at least we know that just test
first program but we have to touch it
it's very important to expiry for the
core so refactoring basically means to
restructure your code without changing
the behavior of the code to to call it
so you clean it up your code without
putting new features and so and there
are I don't know a few thousands of
refactoring so called
who describe what you do there to rename
of methods to move a method whatever
there there are thousands of them and
the ideas actually clean up your code in
this test first programming mindset
clean up your code after you've written
it and after if it works
don't spend too much of your CPU cycles
and do to do it right from the first
time you type your code you have time to
clean up but clean it up as soon as
possible and not someone in the future
yes again this is about courage about
quality oriented working if you see
something that is not good if you see
something that could would be better in
a different way make a note on a piece
of paper beside your keyboard and fix it
as soon as possible and just to make
sure there's no misunderstanding here
modern ideas modern development
environment have supports for
refactoring and that is great and
this sort of refactoring that is
supported by the IDE can be done without
unit tests obviously the IDE takes care
of that the meet that the semantics of
the code is not changed but it isn't
that is not all that there is to effect
when refactoring is actually at looking
at things looking how they what would be
better
what other how to change the design in
order to make the code better and this
often goes beyond the capabilities of
the IDE just to make sure that nobody
says I'm using the Eclipse IDE so I can
do refactoring without unit tests sort
of yes very small refactoring some very
small refactorings but tests are
necessary for refactorings to be
confident to do things that the idea is
not automatically supported and to save
up to make pair programming possible to
make Roble code ownership possible and
stuff like that it's not just unit tests
are not just there for making
refactoring safe so mmhmm yeah okay I
guess we we should end up there the
first experiment here because it's
already very very long episode we didn't
manage to get all our primary practices
in here in the first episode we continue
this in the second one and give you the
rest of overview over the extreme
programming development process thanks
for listening in great to have you and
here you next time
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at sae - radio net
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning Cowley for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license see the soft engineering radio
website for details